Finding Aid for Edward M. Gramlich papers, 1969-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edward M. Gramlich papers 1969-2007
Gramlich, Edward M.
2008159 Aa2
Edward M. Gramlich was a professor of economics and a member of the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve Board. His academic career was primarily associated with the University of Michigan where he taught economics and public policy. He also served as Dean of the School of Public Policy and as Interim Provost. He was a Governor on the Federal Reserve Board from 1997 to 2005. This fragmentary collection mainly represents papers and presentations done by Gramlich, including speeches and interviews recorded on videotape (VHS) and DVD. Some photographs are also included.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records were received in 2007 and 2008 (Donor No. 9972 )
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research without restriction.
Edward M. Gramlich was born in Rochester, New York on June 18, 1939. He graduated with a Bachelor's of Arts from Williams College in 1961. He then completed a Master's (1962) and Doctorate (1965) in Economics at Yale University.
His career was divided between academic institutions and government positions. He began his career in the government at the Research Division of the Federal Reserve Board in 1965. By 1971 he was the Director of the Policy Research Division in the Office of Economic Opportunity and remained there until 1973. In addition to his government work, he was a Senior Fellow at the Brookings Institution for three years (1973-76).
His university career began in 1976 as professor of Economics and Public Policy at the University of Michigan (1976-97). He also served as Director of the Institute of Public Policy Studies (1979-83 and 1991-95), Chair of the Economics Department (1983-86 and 1989-90), and Dean of the School of Public Policy (1995-97). During these years, he returned to government work and served as Deputy Director, and then Acting Director, of the Congressional Budget Office (1986-87).
He left the University of Michigan in 1997 to become a Governor for the Federal Reserve Board. Among his responsibilities, he chaired multiple boards including the Emergency Loan Guarantee Board (1999-2005) and the Air Transportation Stabilization Board (2001-05). While on the Federal Reserve Board, he served as Vice-Chair (1999-2001) and then Chair (2001-05) of the Neighborhood Reinvestment Corporation. He resigned as Governor in 2005.
After his resignation, he returned to the University of Michigan as a professor of economics and public policy. He became Interim Provost at Michigan during 2005-2006.
In addition to numerous citations in the news media, he was the author of many journal articles and a dozen books, primarily dealing with topics of economic and public policy. He was also the principal author of a few major reports, including "The Experiment in Educational Performance Contracting" for the Office of Economic Opportunity, "Staff Analysis" for the Major League Baseball's Economic Study Group and "Report of the 1994-96 Advisory Council on Social Security" for the Social Security Administration.
He died of leukemia on September 5, 2007 at the age of 68. Edward Gramlich and his wife Ruth had two children, Sarah and Robert.
The contents of this collection represent a small fraction of the career of Edward Gramlich. The majority of the collection consists of some of his presentations and speeches. There is also a tiny portion representing other aspects of his professional life: book reviews, reports, a book proposal and news media articles and citations. Where possible, the collection has been organized in chronological order. The papers have been arranged into three series: Papers and Presentations, Topical Files, and Audio-Visual.
Subjects:
Economics.; Fiscal policy--United States.; Gramlich, Edward M.; Social security--United States--Finance.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; DVDs.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Papers and Presentations 1969-2007
  Papers and Presentations contains hard copies of some speeches and presentations that Edward Gramlich gave between 1969 and 2007. They include testimony given before various House and Senate Committees and public speeches to various institutions and organizations. There are some papers where only draft copies are available. Additionally, there are four essays that are undated.
  - Curriculum Vitae (Box 1)
  - 1969
    - Complicated and Simple Approaches to Estimating the Role of Money in Economic Activity June 5, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Recent Experience with the FRB-MIT model November 6, 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970
    - Do Large-Scale Macro Econometric Models have a Keynesian Bias? May 1970 (Box 1)
  - 1971
    - Inflation, Unemployment and the Poverty Problem June 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972
    - An Experiment in Performance Contracting: In the measurement of Educational Effectiveness August 31, 1972 (Box 1)
  - 1972
    - The Demand for Different Skill Classes of Labor October 1972 (Box 1)
  - 1975
    - The Economic and Budgetary Effects of Indexing the Tax System October 1975 (Box 1)
    - The New York City Fiscal Crisis: What Happened and What is to be Done? December 1975 (Box 1)
  - 1976
    - Testimony before the Joint Economic Committee December 3, 1976 (Box 1)
  - 1977
    - Are the Poor Falling Behind? March 1977 (Box 1)
    - Testimony before the Subcommittee on Labor Standards of the House, Education and Labor Committee March 9, 1977 (Box 1)
  - 1978
    - State and Local Budget Surpluses and Federal Grant Policies July 25, 1978 (Box 1)
  - 1981
    - Short and Long Run Income Losses from Recession: A Summary July 1981 (Box 1)
  - 1983
    - Testimony before the Senate Committee on Governmental Affairs Subcommittee April 5, 1983 (Box 1)
  - 1984
    - Conference on Reaganomics: Children's and Families. Comments on Danziger's Speech March 1, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Conditional Grants: A theoretical and Empirical Analysis May 21, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Fair taxes, fast taxes and fouled up taxes June 14, 1984 (Box 1)
  - 1985
    - Tax Reform -- A democratic Issue (Draft) March 1985 (Box 1)
    - Comments on Netzer -- Boston Fed conference October 1985 (Box 1)
  - 1989
    - Dealing with politicians: Some rules for policy analysts (Draft) February 1989 (Box 1)
  - 1990
    - Budget Indicators -- CBO advisers meeting June 19, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Public finance theory and public expenditure policy June 1990 (Box 1)
  - 1991
    - House Budget Committee hearings on the State and Local sector -- Testimony June 13, 1991 (Box 1)
  - 1992
    - Mayor's Blue Ribbon Committee on finance and management presentation to the City Council 1992 (Box 1)
    - Changes in inequality in the 1980s: What happened and what are the implications, September 24, 1992 (Box 1)
  - 1993
    - What should be done about Michigan's local property taxes? (Draft) February 1993 (Box 1)
    - Poor people, poor places (Draft) June 1993 (Box 1)
    - Safety nets and ladders (Draft) December 1993 (Box 1)
  - 1996
    - Subcommittee on Social Security and Family Policy, Senate Finance Committee -- Testimony March 25, 1996 (Box 1)
  - 1998
    - Examining Community Reinvestment November 6, 1998 (Box 1)
  - 1999
    - Macroeconomics: Then and Now April 17, 1999 (Box 1)
    - A stabilization policy strategy April 23, 1999 (Box 1)
  - 2000
    - Social Security reform in the Twenty-first century March 13, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Banking and Financial Services May 24, 2000 (Box 1)
  - 2001
    - The productivity growth spurt in the United States February 20, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Social Security reform in the Twenty-First century April 19, 2001 (Box 1)
    - National saving and treasury debt June 11, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Savings by low-and moderate-income households June 20, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Promoting and sustaining home ownership November 8, 2001 (Box 1)
  - 2002
    - Technology and Labor market conference January 6, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Predatory lending January 18, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Consumption and the wealth effect: The United States and the United Kingdom February 20, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Macroeconomics policy in recessions -- and other times March 7, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Benefit-cost analysis in the public policy process October 16, 2002 (Box 1)
  - 2003
    - Conducting monetary policy January 4, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Loan guarantee programs April 24, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Remarks at the 25th anniversary of the Neighborhood Reinvestment Corporation and the NeighborWorks System August 18, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Maintaining price stability October 1, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Rental housing meeting -- remarks November 14, 2003 (Box 1)
  - 2004
    - Budget and Trade deficits: Linked, both worrisome in the long run, but not twins February 25, 2004 (Box 1)
    - The Board's modeling work in the 1960s, March 26, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Subprime mortgage lending: Benefits, costs and challenges May 21, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Reducing budgets deficits June 24, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Rules for assessing social security reform August 12, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Oil shock and monetary policy September 16, 2004 (Box 1)
  - 2005
    - The importance of raising national saving March 2, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Comments at Princeton conference April 2, 2005 (Box 1)
    - A first step in dealing with growing retirement costs April 21, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Statement before the Committee on Banking, Housing and Urban Affairs May 17, 2005 (Box 1)
    - The politics of inflation targeting May 26, 2005 (Box 1)
    - HMDA data and their effects on mortgage markets June 3, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Social Security reform: One more time September 29, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Another attempt at Social Security reform December 2005 (Box 1)
  - 2006
    - Setting priorities at the UM July 20, 2006 (Box 1)
    - The evolution of thinking about Federal Reserve monetary policy October 28, 2006 (Box 1)
  - 2007
    - Retirement income security February 20, 2007 (Box 1)
    - What to do about the large entitlement spending programs February 21, 2007 (Box 1)
    - Booms and busts, the case of subprime mortgages August 31, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Undated
    - So you think life is easy in Gucci Gulch (Box 1)
    - Yes, deficits do matter (Box 1)
    - More on the income elasticity of Federal personal Income Tax (Box 1)
    - Knowing the difference makes a difference (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  Topical Files includes awards and citations he received. A book proposal includes correspondence surrounding his last book, discussing subprime mortgages. There are also two book reviews he authored. The folder Federal Reserve Board contains a few records around the time of his resignation from the Federal Reserve Board. The News Media files give an overview of his entire body of work and include a listing of citation where his work is cited or he is mentioned. Two reports he participated with ate included: one for the city of Ann Arbor about revenue effects from a city income tax, and an economic study for the Major League Baseball League.
  - Awards 1994-2005 (Box 1)
  - Book Proposal 2007 (Box 1)
  - Book Reviews 2005-2006 (Box 1)
  - Federal Reserve Board 2002-2005 (Box 1)
  - News Media Articles-as Author 1974-2007 (Box 1)
  - News Media Articles-as Subject 1991-2005 (Box 1)
  - News Media Citations 2007-2008, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Reports 1992-1997
    - Report of Independent Members of the Economic Study Committee on Baseball 1992 (Box 1)
    - The Revenue Impact of a city income tax for Ann Arbor 1997 (Box 1)
- Audio Visual
  Audio-Visual contains a collection of photographs of Edward Gramlich. Many of the photographs are undocumented (unknown dates, locations and/or names). Included are group photos of the Federal Reserve Board of Governors. The series also contains various video recordings of television appearances and speeches by Gramlich spanning 1986 - 2007. Most of the recordings are video cassette tapes (VHS), though there are two recordings on DVD format. Also included is a DVD of the memorial service celebrating Gramlich's life. The video recordings have not been viewed to ensure that the title and subject matter correspond.
  - Photographs (individual portraits and groups) circa 1980s-2007 (Box 2)
  - Video Recordings, VHS tapes
    - National Economic Club, Budget and Growth December 15, 1986 (Box 2)
    - OMB Testimony September 10, 1987 (Box 2)
    - C-SPAN Call-in November 11, 1987 (Box 2)
    - Budget Reform, Panel Discussion December 22, 1987 (Box 2)
    - The short and long run economic outlook June 22, 1994 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan Business School, Social Security Reform, Is the system -- or media coverage -- going bust? April 4, 1996, 2 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 2)
    - Lehrer January 6, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Federal Reserve Board Interview, Community Network Television July 23, 1997 (Box 2)
    - FYI (Ann Arbor) July 23, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Nightly Business Report December 30, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Henry George Lecture November 9, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Darden Distinguished Speaker February 15, 2000 (Box 2)
    - NHSA Press Conference at the National Press Club, 65 minutes June 19, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Address to Rutgers University May 30, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Social Security Reform August 12, 2004 (Box 2)
      (C-SPAN Videotape 183081-1 (Part 1 of 1), 39 minutes)
    - Hartwick College November 17, 2004 (Box 2)
    - Ed Gramlich May 9, 2007 (Box 2)
    - The Fed Today Undated (Box 2)
  - DVD Recordings, 3 optical disks DVDs
    - OFN 2006 Keynote Speech, November 1, 2006 (Box 2)
    - C-SPAN, Subprime mortgages July 2007 (Box 2)
    - Ned Gramlich: A celebration of lifetime professional achievements, 95 minutes November 14, 2007 (Box 2)